<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | railey.io</title>
    <link>https://railey.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://railey.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Malcolm R. Railey 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://railey.io/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I decided to attend the University of Texas at Austin for my Master of Science in Data Science</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/post/why-i-decided-to-attend-the-university-of-texas-at-austin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://railey.io/post/why-i-decided-to-attend-the-university-of-texas-at-austin/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;link href=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once I decided to study data science through a formal academic program, I only had to determine whose program to attend?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I decided to attend the Master of Science in Data Science (MSDS) Online at the University of Texas at Austin. I gave my decision much consideration. Here are the reasons that motivate my choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every course taught in the MSDS program is a course I want to take.&lt;/strong&gt; My desired curriculum focuses on using mathematics and statistics, not on using technology. While I value a technical approach to computer science, I don’t believe technology is the starting point for learning data science. As a seasoned computer scientist but a newcomer to data science, I am starting my path with mathematics and applied statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MSDS curriculum &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(UTexas 2021)&lt;/span&gt;, as shown below, illustrates the extent to which UT’s program emphasizes mathematics, statistics, and machine learning. I see only courses that &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; technology, not &lt;em&gt;lead&lt;/em&gt; with technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability and Simulation-Based Inference for Data Science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foundations of Regression and Predictive Modeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Techniques and Theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced Predictive Models for Complex Data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design Principles and Causal Inference for Data-Based Decision Making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Exploration, Visualization, and Foundations of Unsupervised Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principles of Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UT created the MSDS program from the ground-up.&lt;/strong&gt; Clearly, the MSDS program stems directly from data science. Namely, I don’t see any traditional classes in this curriculum from either computer science or applied statistics. That is, the MSDS program is not born of a patchwork of pre-existing courses. Consequently, I anticipate the focus of every discussion to target some aspect of data science. I note that there is no mention of tools, programming languages, or frameworks in this curriculum, which I consider a technical risk but a risk I am willing to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The MSDS Program costs a FLAT FEE of $10,000.&lt;/strong&gt; From my research, no university offers a lower cost Master of Science in Data Science than the University of Texas at Austin, not even Georgia Tech. I consider this pricing disruptive for the industry. While we can all debate the quality of education at one university versus another, we cannot debate the cost. For example, in a recent search, I found the following total costs of a Master of Science in Data Science for eight universities. See Table I below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin:auto center;text-align:center;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table I. Cost of a Master of Science in Data Science,&lt;br/&gt;assuming six semesters spanning three years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin:0 auto;width:75%;&#34;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;University&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Req’d Credits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Total Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ischoolonline.berkeley.edu/admissions/tuition-financial-aid/&#34;&gt;University of California, Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;27 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$78,276&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://viterbigradadmission.usc.edu/programs/masters/msprograms/data-science/ms-applied-data-science/&#34;&gt;University of Southern California&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;32 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$72,644&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ischool.syr.edu/admissions-aid/costs-and-aid/&#34;&gt;Syracuse University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;36 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$64,437&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://datascience.smu.edu/admissions/tuition-and-financial-aid/&#34;&gt;Southern Methodist University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;33.5 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$60,434&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ritchieonline.du.edu/admissions/tuition-and-financial-aid/faq/&#34;&gt;University of Denver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;48 Credit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$51,456&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.illinois.edu/academics/graduate/professional-mcs/online-master-computer-science-data-science&#34;&gt;University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;32 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$21,440&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pe.gatech.edu/degrees/analytics&#34;&gt;Georgia Institute of Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;36 Credits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;$11,706&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ms-datascience.utexas.edu/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Texas at Austin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;33 Credits &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$10,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower cost means more opportunities.&lt;/strong&gt; Using my savings, I can travel to Austin for a conference or meet my professors. I can buy more research materials as required. I can attend additional classes in a specialty. Lower cost gives me the flexibility to learn more and take advantage of the opportunities as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isn’t the MSDS program too new and untested.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, the MSDS program is brand new, starting in Spring 2021, and as such, the program is untested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, I will be a course guinea pig for probably the entire year, but then after one year, I will be engaged in a program that will be firing on all pistons. For a math-oriented program by a major university that costs dramatically less than its nearest competitor, I am willing to take that risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Austin is an exciting place to visit if ever there is such a reason.&lt;/strong&gt; I have no doubt I will visit Austin soon. I want to meet the professors; I want to see the campus; I want to eat the food; I want to hear the music. Besides, I grew up on the UT Austin campus and therefore always appreciate a return visit to my home state of Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the global pandemic of 2020 was brutal to every city’s economy, I firmly believe Austin, as a mecca for high tech &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Bluestein 2020)&lt;/span&gt;, will bounce back in stride, if not with a vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Bluestein2020&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bluestein, Adam. 2020. “Austin Was Destined to Replace Silicon Valley. Then the Pandemic Hit.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://marker.medium.com/austin-was-destined-to-replace-silicon-valley-then-the-pandemic-hit-6d5f5a332e04&#34;&gt;https://marker.medium.com/austin-was-destined-to-replace-silicon-valley-then-the-pandemic-hit-6d5f5a332e04&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-UTexas2021&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UTexas. 2021. “Curriculum &amp;amp; Courses.” &lt;a href=&#34;http://ms-datascience.utexas.edu/courses&#34;&gt;http://ms-datascience.utexas.edu/courses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I decided to pursue a degree in data science</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/post/why-i-decided-to-pursue-a-degree-in-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://railey.io/post/why-i-decided-to-pursue-a-degree-in-data-science/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;link href=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So you want to be a data scientist? Sounds great! I want to be a data scientist, too. So then the question is, what is the best path to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that working towards a formal degree – an online master’s degree – is the best approach. I do not doubt that everyone learns differently. And I recognize that not only everyone is starting from a different position, but also they are seeking a different end-goal. I should therefore clarify those points first as to the basis of my decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning is different for everyone.&lt;/strong&gt; When I learn, I need a well-defined path with both a start and an end. When I read a book, for example, I read every damn page. However, I stop at many points to deep-dive into a question, a challenge, or a background detail. The path keeps me moving forward, while my deep-dive gives me depth and perspective. Yes, I am that person who stops to understand the proofs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Each of us benefits from different learning styles.&lt;/strong&gt; At the same time, it is essential to know what particular learning method works best for you. I learn first by reading and then second by doing. Reading allows me the time to absorb the material in-depth and note areas to revisit later. Unfortunately, I cannot rely on listening as my primary means to learn, which is why I require a companion text. Practice problems help, but not as much as a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have different starting points.&lt;/strong&gt; I already have a Ph.D. in Computer Science, which includes a strong mathematics background (though not a background in applied statistics). Understanding applied statistics, algorithms for machine learning, and data are my challenges, not writing code or learning new technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our end-goals are different.&lt;/strong&gt; As for my end-goal, I am leaving that choice open for now, albeit my options may range from research to consulting. I know that just as I am learning data science online, I plan to work in data science online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How I approach learning.&lt;/strong&gt; Knowing that I plan to listen to content, what I found works best for me is to read and understand the material first and then second use the lecturer’s content to fill in the gap and provide emphasis. My approach implies I need access to written material (e.g., a textbook) for any course I take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isn’t academia boring, long, expensive, and out-of-touch?&lt;/strong&gt; I fully agree that attending a formal program is long, but that’s the only point I agree with here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A master’s program is time-consuming. But then I plan to hit the ground running from the start when I have useful information to work with for an internship or project. Ken Jee &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jee 2020)&lt;/span&gt; calls this having Minimum Viable Knowledge, which is to say, “you should understand just enough of these concepts [in data science] to be able to start exploring your … projects.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is a master’s program expensive? Not really. Today’s graduate programs are quite competitive: Georgia Tech is $11,706 out the door, University of Texas at Austin is a flat-fee of $10,000. Remember, too, that this cash outlay spans several years. In the meantime, I plan to capitalize on my investment early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for whether an academic program is boring or out-of-touch, I believe that measure depends on me. A master’s program is only as strong as I choose to make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So why not just read a bunch of books?&lt;/strong&gt; I know that I can learn data science through any combination of books. On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/&#34;&gt;O’Reilly’s Learning Platform&lt;/a&gt; alone, I found nearly 4,000 books with “data science” relevant to their content. Similarly, I found by Google search many a web page that lists today’s must-read books: “50 Must-Read Free Books For Every Data Scientist in 2020” &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Verma 2020)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, finding a book is not the problem – knowing where to start is my problem. That said, I plan to use my formal study as my primary path and then use supplemental materials along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about following a self-prescribed curriculum?&lt;/strong&gt; I agree wholeheartedly. Not only will I develop my &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; path along the way, but I will also borrow from others’ advice on the same. In particular, I like David Venturi’s &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Venturi 2016)&lt;/span&gt; planned curriculum. I couldn’t agree more with Venturi’s proposal to study what he wants to learn, when he wants to understand it, and how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santiago Víquez Segura [Segura2020] suggests yet another proposal for self-study to include micro-courses by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/learn/overview&#34;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt;. Segura’s suggestions appear attractive and readily achievable, given each micro-course requires less than 4 hours to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am confident that I will combine my academic work with these self-prescribed curriculums along with curriculum suggestions from others, including Sciforce &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Sciforce 2019)&lt;/span&gt; and Paruchrui &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Paruchuri 2020)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why not learn through technology by doing, not by studying?&lt;/strong&gt; I guess so, but I wouldn’t recommend it. I agree that learning through a particular technology grounds you quickly in an application, but doing so also biases you towards one specific train of thought. If all you have is a hammer, then everything looks like a nail. Technologies come and go, if not at least fall into favor or out. Knowing both the why (mathematics, statistics) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the how (technology) is a better, more balanced approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t you need a target industry or domain?&lt;/strong&gt; I do, but for now, I am not targeting a particular industry or field. I am going to see how that plays out as I go along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which do you prefer, technology or theory.&lt;/strong&gt; Ultimately, I decided to start my venture into data science formally. I want to go deep on mathematics and statistics and then learn the appropriate technologies along the way, not vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Jee2020&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jee, Ken. 2020. “How I Would Learn Data Science (If I Had to Start Over).” &lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com/how-i-would-learn-data-science-if-i-had-to-start-over-f3bf0d27ca87&#34;&gt;https://towardsdatascience.com/how-i-would-learn-data-science-if-i-had-to-start-over-f3bf0d27ca87&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Paruchuri2020&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paruchuri, Vik. 2020. “How to Learn Data Science (Step-By-Step) in 2020.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/learn-data-science/&#34;&gt;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/learn-data-science/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Sciforce2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sciforce. 2019. “A Layman’s Guide to Data Science: How to Become a (Good) Data Scientist.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/sciforce/a-laymans-guide-to-data-science-how-to-become-a-good-data-scientist-97927ad51ed8&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/sciforce/a-laymans-guide-to-data-science-how-to-become-a-good-data-scientist-97927ad51ed8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Venturi2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venturi, David. 2016. “My Data Science Master’s: I Dropped Out of School to Create My Own Data Science Master’s– Here’s My Curriculum.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://davidventuri.medium.com/i-dropped-out-of-school-to-create-my-own-data-science-master-s-here-s-my-curriculum-1b400dcee412&#34;&gt;https://davidventuri.medium.com/i-dropped-out-of-school-to-create-my-own-data-science-master-s-here-s-my-curriculum-1b400dcee412&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Verma2020&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verma, Reashikaa. 2020. “50 Must-Read Free Books For Every Data Scientist in 2020.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kdnuggets.com/2020/03/50-must-read-free-books-every-data-scientist-2020.html&#34;&gt;https://www.kdnuggets.com/2020/03/50-must-read-free-books-every-data-scientist-2020.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I want to be a data scientist</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/post/why-i-want-to-be-a-data-scientist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://railey.io/post/why-i-want-to-be-a-data-scientist/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;link href=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some time, I have been writing software to help kids learn math. After so many years to that end, I decided I needed a change of venue: I like software engineering challenges but need a different path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I need to work on more complicated math and computer science; I want to use new programming languages, tools, and frameworks; and I want to work with various domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe working in data science will give me a new sense of direction. Plus, doing so will satisfy my work requirements more broadly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work remotely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in software engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in new areas in computer science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in a domain with boundless opportunity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with challenging math&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work remotely.&lt;/strong&gt; Honestly, I don’t want to move. Of course, I can work locally, but then that would be limiting. Instead, I want to work remotely for whichever company I choose and from wherever I live. Remote work is no longer a limiting choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work in software engineering.&lt;/strong&gt; I like software engineering, from writing code to designing new architectures. I need more challenging problems, from working with complexity and uncertainty to solving scale and design problems. And I need more math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I freely admit that writing production code (software engineering) is both demanding and rewarding. However, writing production code is not where I want to focus my energy; instead, I want to work with something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work in new areas in computer science. &lt;/strong&gt; I am ready to give artificial intelligence a try. I want to solve problems across the board: robotics, vision, natural language processing, planning, machine learning, and deep learning. I can combine my effort in artificial intelligence with my experience in software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to work with data – lots of data. I am speaking about designing structures, writing algorithms, analyzing complexity, and working with architectures for scale and performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work in a domain with boundless opportunity.&lt;/strong&gt; When I was a consultant, I always told myself, “there is always room for one in the movie theater.” I don’t need to find the funding for 20 engineers; I only need to find the funding for one (me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then again, securing even one seat as a software engineer is hard: you need to write a lot of code. On the other hand, securing a seat as a data scientist could be easy (no production code required): you need a path to a strong recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the path, not writing the code, is the difference. And, as for finding that path, the sky is the limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work with challenging math.&lt;/strong&gt; I like the idea of adding complicated math – applied statistics – to my work results. To that end, I am motivated to learn everything I can about applied statistics, machine learning, deep learning and then use today’s technology to build upon that knowledge. I find it interesting that old topics in statistics are now considered fresh and innovative thanks to technological advances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately, I like knowing that the path I want to follow is a data scientist’s path leading to the most desired job. In their article for Harvard Business Review &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Davenport and Patil 2012)&lt;/span&gt;, Davenport and Patil describe the data scientist’s position as just that: “Data Scientist: The Sexiest Job of the 21st Century.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their article, Davenport and Patil describe a point of innovation at LinkedIn when a scientist – Jonathon Goldman – recognized the implied social connections between LinkedIn’s users. Specifically, Goldman recognized the pattern of “triangle closing”, which is to say that “if you know Larry and Sue, there’s a good chance that Larry and Sue know each other” &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Davenport and Patil 2012)&lt;/span&gt;. And from that discovery, Goldman and his team gave birth to LinkedIn’s feature, “People You May Know,” which launched LinkedIn onto its meteoric path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldman’s discovery stems from the data, not from the code – my point exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Davenport2012&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davenport, Thomas H., and D. J. Patil. 2012. “Data Scientist: The Sexiest Job of the 21st Century.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2012/10/data-scientist-the-sexiest-job-of-the-21st-century&#34;&gt;https://hbr.org/2012/10/data-scientist-the-sexiest-job-of-the-21st-century&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
