<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About | railey.io</title>
    <link>https://railey.io/about/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://railey.io/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>About</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Malcolm R. Railey 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://railey.io/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/about/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>About This Website</title>
      <link>https://railey.io/about/about-this-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://railey.io/about/about-this-website/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;link href=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://railey.io/rmarkdown-libs/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This website is a running commentary on my study and practice of a new discipline called &lt;strong&gt;data science&lt;/strong&gt;. I call this discipline &lt;strong&gt;applied statistics&lt;/strong&gt; when speaking to my friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2021 – Let the games begin!&lt;/strong&gt; I decided over a year ago to study &lt;a href=&#34;https://railey.io/post/why-i-want-to-be-a-data-scientist/&#34;&gt;data science&lt;/a&gt; formally through an academic program. To that end, I applied to and was accepted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ms-datascience.utexas.edu/&#34;&gt;Master of Science in Data Science Online&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need for change.&lt;/strong&gt; For some time, I have been writing software to help kids learn math. After so many years to that end, I decided I needed a venue change: I like software engineering challenges but need a different path. I need new math and computer science challenges, including working with new programming languages, new tools, and new frameworks. For more on why I am affecting a change, see my post on &lt;a href=&#34;post/why-i-want-to-be-a-data-scientist/&#34;&gt;Why I want to be a data scientist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting a degree.&lt;/strong&gt; While studying data science is not a stretch for me, doing so for a formal degree is: I already have a Ph.D. in Computer Science plus years of experience in software engineering. Learning a new topic is certainly not a surprise choice on my part. I have always been a life-long learner, studying new topics in technology, mathematics, and taxation. I buy used math books through Amazon, subscribe annually to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/online-learning/&#34;&gt;O’Reilly Learning Platform&lt;/a&gt;, and most recently signed up for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/courseraplus&#34;&gt;Coursera Plus&lt;/a&gt;. Nonetheless, I decided to take the plunge. To learn more, please see my post on &lt;a href=&#34;post/why-i-decided-to-pursue-a-degree-in-data-science/&#34;&gt;Why I chose to pursue a degree in data science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attending UT Austin.&lt;/strong&gt; Many universities offer graduate programs in data science online. So then the question is where should I attend school. I am motivated to attend UT Austin for several reasons, including UT’s commitment to an in-depth mathematical approach to applied statistics, not to mention my hometown attachment to UT Austin. To learn more about my decision, please see my post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://railey.io/post/why-i-decided-to-attend-the-university-of-texas-at-austin/&#34;&gt;Why I decided to attend the University of Texas at Austin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
